Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 136, 1870-1899; 136; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a neat and compact hand (4mm), framed with an ornamented border colored in red and yellow, and occasionally green with vine motifs. 4 talismanic drawings or paintings. A string for suspending the scroll is sewn to the top edge. (Box 4)
  Large drawing (280 x 145mm) of Christ (?) seated between two columns filled with the heads of demons (colored grey), with the supine figure of a beaten devil below along with the archangel Michael holding a drawn sword. (In ink with grey, yellow, red, green and vibrant blue color.)
  Above the painting is the text (in Amharic): "Lest no one damage this book, let him be excommunicated by the power of Peter and Paul."
  Three haloed figures. (In ink with red, yellow, green and vibrant blue color.)
  Two archangels with drawn swords. (In ink with green, yellow, red and vibrant blue color.) Eight-pointed star design with central face and animal heads in the four quadrants. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Mädhen (f.), overwritten with the name of W. Abiyyä Egzi' (f.)
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and Barya, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Zar; Prayer against Evil Spirits, Including Accounts of the Story of the Gadarene Swine from the Gospel of Matthew and the Man Possessed by Evil Spirits from the Gospel of Mark; Prayer from the Gospel of Luke; Opening of the Gospel of John; Prayers for Dispelling Demons, Some Invoking the Secret Names of Solomon, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 137, 1850-1899; 137; 5 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (3-5mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Eight-pointed star with central face. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Derivative eight-pointed star design with each point terminating in a serpent's head. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Angel with drawn sword striking down a demon. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Cross design. (In ink with red color.)
  Owner: Gäbrä Sellasé (m.) – the text suggests the scroll was originally drafted for a woman, as well as for a man.
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons (Ma'esäromu Lä'aganent), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Buda. Another Prayer for the Binding of Demons, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells (Fethatä Seray), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, Buda, Barya and Légéwon, etc, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 138, early/mid 19th century; 138; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a neat and compact hand (3mm). There are no drawings. The beginning of the scroll is missing. 675 x 110mm (Box 4)
  A Long, unnamed prayer for dispelling demons by secret names and invoking the archangels Gabriel and Michael. Account of secret names and words given (by God ?) to man and the "Sons of Abraham" for protection from evil [incomplete]. Beginning in abrupto.
  Owner: Sergutä Sellasé (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 139, 1870-1899; 139; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in a sloping, angular hand (4-5mm), framed and divided by a border with a scalloped design with yellow color. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Archangel with drawn sword with lattice-work borders above and below. (In ink with orange-red, yellow and blue color.)
  Cruciform design surrounded by eight heads enclosed between two borders of lattice-work design. (In ink with orange-red, yellow and blue color.)
  Derivative eight-pointed star design with central face enclosed within a lozenge-shape, four further faces in the corners. (In ink with orange-red, yellow and blue color.)
  - Prayer for Binding Demons (Ma'esäromu Läganent [sic]), late 19th century; 1 item
    Includes the prayer of Susenyos. The text includes (col. 1) a grid chart of letters and numbers,
  - Prayer or Sequence of Prayers for Binding Demons Including Qurañña, Buda, S'ela Wogi [sic] and Shutälay [sic], late 19th century; 1 item
    The text further includes (col. 2) a grid chart of letters.
  - Prayer against Miscarriage, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 140, 1830-1870; 140; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a large and angular hand (5mm), framed within a simple scalloped border in ink. 3 talismanic drawings. A string for suspension is sewn to the top of the scroll. (Box 4)
  Roughly drawn square and four circles above a pair of squares with schematic cruciform infill. (In ink with traces of red color.)
  Set of talismanic figures. (In ink with some red color.)
  Guardian angel. (In ink with some red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Abnä Wäld (m.)
  - The Text Known as the Net of Solomon, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Includes prayers for binding demons, barya, etc.,
  - Prayer Entitled "The Maturity of Solomon" (Lehqätä Sälomon), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 141, 1850-1899; 141; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an angular and uneven hand (3-4mm), framed between a simple linear border with traces of yellow color. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Cruciform design comprising a central face and four faces or heads as the arms, with four further small crosses in each corner, enclosed between decorated borders containing various eye motifs. (In ink with red, yellow and some faded blue color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow, red, blue and green color.)
  Eight-pointed star with central face and checkerboard pattern in the four corners. (In ink with red, yellow and some faded green color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Mika'él (f.) – the given name Denqenäsh is added once to this baptismal name.
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage. Another Prayer against Hemorrhage and Miscarriage, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Successful Conception and Childbirth, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons and against the Evil Eye, "Evil and Accursed Barya", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and Miscarriage, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Disease of Shätolay [sic], circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache, Mäggañña and Shätolay, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 142, 1850-1899; 142; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a small, moderate hand (2-3mm), framed within a simple linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Finely drawn figure of a guardian angel holding a drawn sword. (In ink with orange-red, blue, purple and faint yellow color.)
  Angel. (In ink with orange-red, yellow, purple and blue color.)
  Cross. (In ink with purple, yellow and blue color.)
  - Secret Names of Solomon for Binding Demons and the Text Known as the Net of Solomon. Secret Names of God for Protection from Evil Spirits, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons (Ma'esäromu Lä'aganent) Spoken by Alexander "On Friday Before Gog and Magog", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Aqweyas', Légéwon and Gudalé, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Nädära and Barya, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Blacksmiths, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Buda and Blacksmiths, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sorcerers, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
    The text contains a few talismanic figures and a grid chart of letters (both in purple ink).
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 143, circa 1850-1899; 143; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. The top of the scroll has been cut away and the bottom section is missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (in purple ink) in a moderate hand (3mm). 2 talismanic drawings. The scroll is much stained and rubbed and the text is illegible in parts. 970 x 85mm (Box 4)
  The text known as the Net of Solomon. Secret names of God for protection from evil spirits [incomplete].
  Guardian angel (cut off from the upper chest.) (In ink with yellow, purple and faded green color.)
  Eight-pointed star with central face. (In ink with faded yellow color.)
  Owner: Amätä Rufa'él (f.) inserted over erasure.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 144, 1850-1899; 144; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in an uneven and untidy hand (3-5mm), separated a central margin with an eye motif design. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Cruciform design. (In ink, no color.) Large cruciform design with central face and surrounded by sets of concentric circles. (In ink, no color.)
  Large ovoid design divided into eight panels, four of which contain seraphim drawn in a markedly European manner. (In ink, no color.)
  Two archangels holding drawn swords, also drawn in a European manner. Above them are two circles, one with rays ending in smaller circles, the other with a central face within three further concentric circles. On the right is a small hand-cross figure. The accompanying text reads, "save thy servant Wäldä Mika'él."
  Owners: Kinä Sellasé (m.); in the drawings the name Wäldä Mika'él (m.) occurs.
  - Secret Names of Solomon for Binding Demons (The Net of Solomon), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Protection from "Evil Blacksmiths"; Prayers against Various Demons and Evil Spirits, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons (Ma'esäromu Lä'aganent), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Expelling Demons (Seddätä Aganent), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer "For Subduing Enemies", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
    Followed by other untitled prayers comprising mostly magical names (asmat.).
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 145, 1830-1870; 145; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (3-4mm), now somewhat faded and rubbed, and framed within a wide border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. The top of the scroll shows some worm damage. Preserved in half a leather cylinder case. (Box 4)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face and curling arms. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Guardian angel holding a drawn sword, protecting a figure on the right from a demon on the left. (In ink with red, yellow and faded blue color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red, yellow and blue color.)
  Owner: Wäldä Heywät (m.) with the given name Yätämäññu.
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, Aynä Wärq and Demons of the Air (Aganentä Ayär) ... Fälasha and Zar, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Disease of Däsaso (?) and Gwergeho (?), Continuing With a Prayer for Protection from Blacksmiths, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Includes the secret names of Solomon.
  - Prayer of St. Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, Gärgari and Algum, Däsk and Gudalé "And All Hostile Forces", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, Barya and Zar, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, and the "Barya of Stomach Ache", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 146, 1830-1870; 146; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an untidy hand (3-4mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face and stylized eye motifs and semicircles in the four quadrants. (In ink with yellow and red color.)
  Guardian angel holding a drawn sword. (In ink with faded red and yellow color.)
  Derivative eight-pointed star design comprising a central face enclosed within a lattice and framed by four circles with checkerboard infill in each corner. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Lattice-work knot design incorporating eye motifs; the text reads, "there is nothing that is impossible for God. Wälättä Maryam."
  - Prayer for the Protection of the Soul Invoking the Secret Names of God, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Satan, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Accursed Légéwon "Who Cuts the Hearts of Men"; Prayers against Various Devils, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 147, 1830-1870; 147; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a thick, square hand (5mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face and curling arms, perhaps described by the words harägä wäyn "vine" written in red across the bottom of the drawing. Above and below are borders with cross and chevron motifs. (In ink with yellow and red color.)
  Eleven-pointed sun-figure identified by the text "appearance of the sun" written twice across the drawing. (In ink with yellow and some red color.)
  Small central face within a square from which radiate four horn-like arms, the whole set against a series of concentric squared circles decorated on the outer edge by small crosses. Above and below are borders with cross-hatch and cruciform decoration. The text identifies the figure as "the face of Mélos." (In ink with yellow and red-brown color.)
  Rough drawing of a cruciform shape with a central face surrounded by four smaller crosses linked by a frame decorated with yet smaller crosses. The name Wäldä Esra'él is written across the top of the drawing. (In ink with yellow and red-brown color.)
  Owner: the name Wälättä Yohannes (f.) has been inserted in small letters in the spaces left for the owner's name and over erasures; the original owner's name may just be made out as Wälättä Aqlesya (f.)
  - Opening of the Gospel of John, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells (Fethatä Seray), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Denial of Satan and the Demons of the Air (Kehdätä Säyt'an Yä'ayär Aganent [sic]), the King of Nuba and the Demons of the Sea, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Diseases of the Heart, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 148, 1830-1870; 148; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven and widely spaced hand (3-4mm), framed with in a simple linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Guardian angel holding a drawn sword with four smaller figures behind. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Crowned figure holding a berellé or wine flask, accompanied by attendants, one holding a parasol and the other a fly-whisk.
  Sun figure with a square face at the center, the whole enclosed within a square. (In ink with red-brown and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Sellasé (f.); the name Wälättä Maryam (f.) has been inserted in several places over erasures.
  - Prayer against Diseases of Demons, Buda and S'ela Wägi, Fälasha and Eslam, Invoking the Secret Names of God, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer of St. Susenyos "For the Removal of Disease", mid 19th century; 1 item
    Includes the legend of Susenyos.
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Pollution or Defilement (Dänäs), mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 149, 1800-1850; 149; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a small, reasonable hand (3mm). 4 talismanic drawings and 1 series of talismanic figures. There is considerable worm damage at the top of the scroll. Preserved in a leather cylinder case. (Box 4)
  Grid pattern with alternate cross and face infill designs. Below is a border of rosette and chevron motifs. The upper part of the drawing is now missing owing to extensive damage at the top of the scroll. (In ink with faded red and yellow color.) The text written in the border reads, "in the name of the Father."
  Crowned figure holding a drawn sword. Again the text on the left of the drawing reads, "in the name of the Father." (In ink with red-brown and yellow color.)
  Eight-pointed star with central face; the points of the star end in extravagant curls. Below is a border of rosettes. (In ink, uncolored except for some red in the central rosette.)
  Hand-cross design. The word "cross" is written in red in the center. Below is a band of rosettes. (In ink, uncolored except for some red on the cross.)
  A series of talismanic designs and a grid chart with letters, reading "Alpha and O[mega] Jesus."
  Owner: Kidanä Maryam (m.) written over erasures.
  - Prayer for the Protection of the Soul Invoking the Secret Names of God, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Diseases of Barya and "Foul Légéwon That Cuts the Hearts of Men", early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Stomach Ailments, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 150, 1830-1870; 150; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a moderate hand (3-4mm). 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved within a leather double cyclinder case. (Box 4)
  A row of six heads between ornamented borders of chevron and looped-cross designs. (In ink with faded red and yellow color.)
  Three-tiered drawing: first row, alternate cross with eye motifs and head-and-shoulder figures; second row, three crowned figures separated by crosses; third row, a central head-and-shoulder figure with eye-motif and circle filled squares either side. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Cross with two figures either side. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Liqanos (f.) The name Wälättä Giyorgis (f.) has been added over erasures in five instances.
  - Prayer against the Disease of Shotälay; Prayers against Hemorrhage and Miscarriage, mid 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. The first prayer includes an invocation of the secret names of Solomon.
  - Prayer against "The Calamity of Disease" (Mäqsäftä Däwé), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer of St. Susenyos. Legend of St. Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Successful Conception, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Buda, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 151, 1830-1870; 151; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (3-5mm). 4 talismanic drawings. The edges of the upper part of the scroll show some damage. (Box 4)
  Central sun-face motif within a circle decorated by four seraphim or winged heads. Below is a border of simple rosette or lobed cross designs. (In ink with some red color.)
  Eight-pointed star design within a circle surmounted on a shaft; from the circle extend four feather-like arms, and the whole is surrounded by six small circles containing eye motifs. (In ink with some red color.)
  Three hand-crosses and two square faces. (In ink with some red color.)
  Winged head surmounting a small cube-like body. The text reads "guardian angel." (In ink with red color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been overwritten throughout by that of Zämaryam (m.)
  - The Text Known as the Net of Solomon; Prayers against Däsk, Gudalé, Barya and Légéwon and Other Evil Spirits, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya and Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 152, circa 1850-1899; 152; 1 box Single piece of parchment. 1 col., written in black without rubrics in an indifferent hand (3-4mm). 2 talismanic drawings. The bottom portions of the scroll are missing. 830 x 65mm (Box 4)
  Prayer for undoing spells [incomplete].
  Eight-pointed star with central face and curling arms. (In ink with yellow color.)
  Owner: none identified.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 153, 1770-1830; 153; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an exceptionally well-formed and regular hand (4-5mm). 2 talismanic drawings. The top, bottom and edges of the scroll show extensive rodent damage, and both the beginning and end of the scroll are now missing. (Box 4)
  Cruciform design divided into five squares each filled with transverse or lobed cross motifs; between the arms of the cross are bird-head motifs and each arm of the cross is surmounted by a trefoil or semicircular motif. Above is a vine-like border, and below a simple band of semicircles. (In ink with yellow and pinkish red color.)
  Another cruciform design with lobed infill between the arms of the cross and axe-head motifs at the end of each arm. Above and below are decorated borders. (In ink with yellow and pinkish red color.)
  - Prayer against Colic (?) (Qwe[rs'ät]) and Mäggañña, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
    only partially preserved and unidentified.
  - Prayer against Colic and Mäggañña. Another Prayer against Colic and Mäggañña, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism or General Pain, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Demons and Devils, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer for Drowning Demons (Mäst'emä Aganent); Prayer against Spell-Casting Buda and Evil Légéwon, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 154, 1870-1899; 154; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in a moderate and widely-spaced hand (4-5mm), framed within a lattice-work border with red and yellow color, and separated by a central margin some of which is colored red and contains eye motifs and the rest is left plain and colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Large guardian spirit figure, the head of which is formed of a two-headed serpent which encircles the prominent eyes; the body with its raised arms is reduced to a a block of overlapping scale-motifs. (In ink with red, yellow and blue color.)
  Abunä Samu'él riding a lion; the text reads, "the lion of Samu['él]." (In ink with yellow, red and blue color.)
  Two angelic figures and a demon (?) (In ink with red, green and blue color.)
  Owners: Zämaryam (m.) and Wälättä Täklä Haymanot (f.); the latter name is twice replaced by that of Wälättä Kidan (f.)
  - Prayer for Binding Demons (Ma'esäromu Lä'aganent), Invoking the Secret Names of God, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Drowning Demons (Mäst'emä Aganent), late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Buda. Another Prayer for Binding Demons, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic or Stomach Ache. Mälke'a Fanu'él (Hymn Of Salutation to the Archangel Phanuel, the "Banisher of Demons"), late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism or General Pain, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 155, late 19th century; 155; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a poor hand (2-3mm). 2 talismanic drawings. The bottom portion of the scroll is missing. 875 x 87mm (Box 4)
  Prayer against Hemorrhage (?) Prayer and Legend of St. Susenyos [incomplete].